Today we are celebrating here,
in this Holy land,
the birthday of Shri Krishna.
Shri Krishna is the ultimate,
of the Fatherhood that I described to you before,
Who came on this earth,
and illustrated the ultimate of that.
So on this earth the highest Fatherhood is,
Shri Krishna's awareness.
But in the Kingdom of God, we can say in the,
Heavens or even above everything else,
resides Sadashiva who does not take incarnations.
He is one of the aspects; Shri Krishna
is one of the aspects of Sadashiva which is the Father.
And the Adi Shakti or the Holy Ghost
is the other aspect of Sadashiva which is His Power.
So when Shri Krishna incarnated on this earth,
an aspect of this Adi Shakti
came on this earth as Radha.
She's the same who came as the Mother of Christ,
and She gave the name of Christ,
as the surname of Shri Krishna,
as if it's Shri Krishna's name Krishna, from Krishna.
He's called as Krist in Indian languages - Krist.
And I have told you before why He was called as Jesu or Yesu.
So today we are going to see to the two aspects of Shri Krishna,
which were the manifestation of His Divine birth.
In Rama's life they showed a man,
a purushottama the best of the Father in worldly affairs.
And in Shri Krishna's life they showed Him,
the highest Fatherhood as in Yogeshwara
or in Divine world.
So the first aspect of Krishna we have to understand
is the Yogeshwara,
and the second aspect of Him as the Virata.
Yogeshwara means the Lord of the Yoga,
or the power of Yoga.
He is called because He reached the,
optimum that one has to reach as a yogi.
As if He's the ideal that you have to reach.
Now as a Yogi He was born of a royal family
but He lived in the jungles, in the forest,
with the cows, with ordinary people.
He used to sleep on the ordinary places
like sometimes on the stone or on the grass
when He would go with His cows for their feeding.
Secondly He was very, very aware,
absolutely aware of His powers,
without any Ego.
He had a special power called samharashakti
by which He could destroy all those people
who tried to harm the Divine manifestation.
The samharashakti is expressed
as the chakra in His hand.
And another is the gada in His Hand.
These powers were within Him and,
He acted according to the power of Radha
because She was the One
who sustained the power of Shri Krishna.
The proof of that is this, that
when He was in Gokul with Radha He did all his
samhara, work samharakarya
and afterwards He just became a sarti
- is a chariot driver for Arjuna.
So for His disciple Arjuna He became even a chariot driver.
The another great quality of Yogeshwara was
the complete discretion power built in.
So He knew who was a devil and who was not,
who is good, who is bad;
who is possessed, who is not possessed;
who is innocent who is not.
This was built in within Him, this power,
of complete discrimination.
And He had a capacity,
more expressing His witness hood, as a sakshi.
He had a capacity, I mean He was a sakshi Himself.
l should say this way is easier to understand.
He was a sakshi means He had the capacity
of witnessing the whole world as a play.
At the time of Rama, Rama was,
the one who got involved into His problems,
to show as if He is a full human being.
So that human should not say that He was God
so how could we accept God
because He was God after all.
Now this capacity in Him to witness,
has to be seen in every yogi.
The element He controls is ether.
We call it as akasha in Sanskrit.
This ether as you know we are using now
for our television, for our radio,
for every sort of a collective work.
So we have to be
in charge of the ether element, as yogis.
And that is the subtlest of all, in the sense that,
you permeate into everything with that.
And is above all, like plastic also permeates into everything
into matter, into everything up to the air.
But it cannot enter into ether.
So the negativity cannot enter into ether.
So when you enter into your ethereal zone,
you actually enter into the area,
which is thoughtless awareness.
So to achieve your ethereal state
you have to expand your thoughtless awareness.
And the sustenance of that is done by Christ, by the Spirit.
So you can realize now as a yogi,
your state of mind should be ethereal.
And what should be the state of your superego
- this is the ego part of it that
you should be in ethereal state -
and as a superego you should see it as a play.
You should see the play of the negative.
Negativity will run away but don't get involved into it,
play into their hands,
then the negativity will separate from you.
So the ego and superego both rise from the visshuddhi chakra.
They can be receded by the agnya chakra
but are to be sucked in the visshuddhi.
The greatest quality of Yogeshwara is that
He is not at all involved into anything,
detached absolutely.
If He eats His food He does not eat it,
if He speaks He does not speak,
if He sees He does not see,
if He hears He does not hear.
It has no effect on Him, no retention on it,
no action on it.
Whatever He is He is complete.
Sixteen petals is complete mould,
sixteenth day of the moon is the Purnima is the.
That is how one has to be, complete in oneself,
complete confidence in oneself.
But the confidence should not be confused with ego.
But confidence is complete wisdom, is complete dharma.
It is complete love, complete beauty,
and is complete God.
That's what it should be.
Now when He said that you give up
all your dharmas and surrender to me in Gita
what He was meaning -
that all other things about which you are worried you give up
and become, one with me so I look after you.
Give up the responsibility to Shri Krishna.
So the complete integrated Divinity
will start expressing through you.
Means if you say that you have to be responsible,
then He says: 'All right go ahead, try.'
But if you say, that you are responsible,
I am just an institution or an instrument in Your hand,
then, you start manifesting it well,
and that is how your visshuddhi chakra gets opened out.
This is some part of the Yogeshwara l have spoken to you.
But as He is the brain within us,
He becomes the brain within us.
We have to know all the qualities of a Divine brain,
are with Him.
So whatever we do with our brain,
like intrigue, thieving,
the deception,
all which are bad things by your brain as they call it,
are done by Him for the Divine purpose,
without getting any blemish upon Himself.
And the other side of it whatever we do,
so called positive, like politics or like diplomacy,
like leadership,
all that is,
His Own doing, like even the thinking,
of the future and all that He does for us
- planning, thinking all those things, administration -
as a play, everything is done as a play,
because He is the Master, as we call as a sutradara
the one who does the prologue in a drama
the one who plays with the strings, with the pantomimes.
Now the other thing that we have to understand,
Shri Krishna at this stage of Sahaja Yoga,
that it is the Virata Shakti that is manifesting at this time,
and not the Shri Krishna Shakti which was at His time.
And the power that is working here is no more
that of Radha, or of Mary, but of Viratangana.
That's why the knowledge of Sahaja Yogis is,
much wider,
than the knowledge of all the Saints, of ages.
But is not deeper than them.
If you can deepen your knowledge,
this wider knowledge will have proper roots within you.
So the brain are the roots,
here are the roots of the whole, tree of life.
Actually Kundalini comes up and waters the brain first
so that the whole tree of life is
drenched in the Divine bliss, and Divine knowledge.
So this Virata Shakti that we have to work out
gives us the sense of collective consciousness first.
First we understand it through our brainpower.
But the whole brainpower is to be guided by the heart.
Is to be, watered
but in Sanskrit is a very beautiful word sinchena -
like dewdrops you see, sprayed with the love of God.
So the integration of this brain
has to take with heart and with your liver.
Then only the Virata Shakti takes another form.
The weapons of killing, become the weapons of forgiveness.
Every sort of destructive power is used for the construction,
as if it is tricked,
like now I told them a trick how to trick these gurus.
The power that they have can be tricked against them
as He said that their teeth must be put into their necks,
into their throats.
Instead of taking out their teeth
better put them back into their own throats.
And if you can do that, then there is no problem,
as far as their effect on us is concerned
because you are more powerful and more tricky.
Because the Virata Shakti has now taken that form.
Like the tree when it grows it grows upward,
but when it is laden with fruit it comes down.
First it is attractive by its flowers,
by its timber, by its all other parts of its body.
And people try to destroy it for it.
But when the fruits appear they want to preserve it,
and the tree bends down, its humility is very valuable.
So you are the fruits,
that Viratangana Shakti, you are the fruits.
Because you are so valuable,
that those people who wanted to ruin
or to destroy the Divine power from this earth
will start thinking that
they have to gain something out of these fruits.
So today the Virata Shakti has given you a great value,
because people see that by having
one Sahaja Yogi with them it is so precious.
Say one ordinary man gets his Realization,
then he develops his value,
in that - his own value, he can be respected, loved
and given the highest, if he's a proper Sahaja Yogi.
So you should understand today that Virata Shakti is-
we are going to worship that Virata Shakti
which has given fruits.
As a result of that all these different churches
and fanaticism and atheism, and communism
and all that 'ism' - all these will neutralize
because they will see they've benefited it.
But you have to become that,
that is the biggest thing one has to know
is to bend down towards the Mother Earth,
to be humble.
Absolutely the humility inside out,
is really going to give you
the complete value of Sahaja Yoga fruits.
Those Sahaja Yogis who boast about themselves
are like the fruits which are getting ruined
only on the tree.
The only fruits which bend down
are accepted as good and matured fruits
and not those who assert that they are the highest.
But some of the negative people
should not by any chance take advantage of this,
and say that, they are good
because they are bending down, it's not the logic.
Some of them boast they are humble,
even a rotten fruit bends down.
But the matured fruit,
shows its humility by its weight.
That is the Guru tattwa, weight.
So from the Viratangana power,
we get the power of maturity up to the fruit
and then we become blessed by Guru Principle.
Those who are still involved,
in getting to better sunshine,
or getting to better water supply,
or all these things are not yet matured
because the fruit doesn't need anything anymore.
It doesn't need anything from the Mother Earth,
nor from the elements.
But it surrenders, it bends, it bows to the Mother Earth.
So the Sahaja Yogi who goes on asking questions to Mother,
bringing personal problems, stupid ideas, negativity,
all those people are still not yet the fruits.
But the matured people are those who surrender,
who bow to the Mother Earth.
So the capacity to bow is the best judgment of yourself;
and leaving everything,
to the power of gravity of Your Mother
to do every work for you;
and leaving all your small little worries behind.
You have to rise above, these restricting powers.
And achieve the completion of this Virata Shakti,
which ultimately becomes a madhura Shakti,
madhura. There's no word in English language
but it means a sweet power.
Like the fruit becomes sweet,
that's how you all have to become very sweet.
Krishna tried to make everything very sweet in the sense
it was all madhura shakti that was acting,
all His play, all His dancing,
all His stories if you read
is nothing but madhura shakti
- towards gopas and gopis,
towards other Sahaja Yogis.
So you have to keep your Mother pleased
by pleasing all other Sahaja Yogis,
and not other people, they are not important.
So today we are going to shorten the Puja
and that's why it took so much time upstairs to shorten it.
So the time lost is time gained forever and ever.
May God bless you all.